Our player can now move their ship
我们的玩家现在可以
around the game area and it can't
在游戏区域内移动
leave the bounds of the game.
已经不会跑到游戏区域外面了
So now let's create shots
现在让我们开始制作一些
for our player to shoot.
射击出去的子弹
First let's begin by deactivating
首先让我们把玩家对象
our player game object.
无效化
This assignment won't involve the players ship
因为制作发射子弹的任务不会影响到玩家飞船
and again it will simply be in the way.
玩家飞船的存在只回影响我们观察
Next create a new empty game object
下一步建立一个空的游戏对象
Use shift+command+N on the Mac
Mac上使用shift+command+N
and shift+control+N on Windows.
Windows上使用shift+control+N
Rename the new empty game object Bolt.
将新的空的游戏对象命名为Bolt
This will be a parent game object for our shot.
这个是我们射击子弹的的父对象
We are going to separate the game logic
我们要把游戏逻辑
from our visual effect of the shot.
和视觉特效分开
This will allow us to easily make new
这样我们可以更通过对父对象的复用
weapons with different visual effects
轻松的创建
by reusing the parent game object with the
效果各异的新武器
logic and replacing the visual effect layer
仅需要对特效层面做一个改变
Reset the game object's transform to make
把游戏对象变形插件重置一下
sure it is at origin.
保证其处在原点
Now create a quad to hold our
现在新建一个quad(四边形)来保存我们
visual effect image, just like we did
的特效图像,做法跟我们在背景那章讲
for our background.
的一样
Rename the quad VFX
把quad改名为VFX
and reset the quad's transform.
重置一下quad的变形插件
Now add the VFX game object
把VFX对象作为Bolt
as a child of Bolt.
的子对象进行添加
If we switch to the Scene view we can see the quad
如果我们切回场景视图模式
just like the one we used for the background
quad跟我们之前的背景的情况是一样的
is oriented in a way we can't see
它在原点的角度正好让我们
with our game view camera.
无法从相机中看到它
Change the transform rotation X to 90.
把变形插件rotation X的值设置为90
This will rotate the quad to face upwards
这样就会把quad的表面朝向变成向上
towards the game view camera.
正好面对了相机
See, it's perfectly face-on to
看吧,游戏视图中
camera in the game view.
它正好面对着相机
Let's make this shot look like a laser bolt.
我们把这个射出去的子弹变得像一个激光子弹
So next we need to find artwork
我们需要找到激光子弹
for our laser bolt.
对应的图片
Open the Textures folder.
打开Textures文件夹
In the Textures folder find  fx_laser_orange.
找到文件fx_laser_orange
When we created the background
我们建背景的时候
we simply dragged the nebula texture
我们只是把星云的纹理
on to the background quad and allowed
拖拽到了背景的quad上
Unity to make the material for us.
让Unity自己生成的材料
This time let's not drag the texture
这次我们换种方法
on to the quad, but let's create
我们自己创建并指定
and assign the material ourselves.
材料
We want to create a new material
我们将在Materials文件夹新建
in the Materials folder.
一种新材料
When we create a new asset
当我们新建一个资源的时候
Unity will create that asset in the
Unity 会在我们当前察看的
folder we have focused or in the
文件夹中新建
same folder as the asset we are currently inspecting.
资源
Select the Materials folder in the
在Assets的跟层级目录选定
root level of Assets.
Materials文件夹
With the Materials folder selected click on
选定Materials文件夹后点击
the Create menu in the Project view
Project(项目)视图中的Create菜单
and select Material.
选择Material
This creates a new material
这样就在Materials 文件夹中
in the Materials folder.
创建了一个新的材料
The new material is ready for a new name.
新的材料需要一个新名字
So let's rename the material fx_bolt_orange.
我们命名为fx_bolt_orange
We want to add our texture
我们需要增加我们的纹理
fx_laser_orange to our material, but how?
把fx_laser_orange贴到材料上,但是怎么做呢
If we can't inspect the details of a material
如果我们不能查看材料的细节
it's inspector may be collapsed.
那么这个查看器可能是已经崩溃了
Click on the Materials header to expand the
如果材料查看器面板关闭了
Materials Inspector panel if it's closed.
就点一下材料的标题栏
We can now see all of the fields
我们现在可以看到当前材料的全部
for this material.
字段
There are 2 ways we can associate
这里有2种方法来
a texture with this material.
把材料和纹理关联起来
The first is, in the Materials
第一种方法是,点击材料的主纹理
main texture field we can click on Select
方框,这时会弹出一个
and this will bring up an Asset Picker.
资源选择器
At the top of the asset picker is a search
资源选择器的顶端是
field to refine the contents of the picker.
帮助我们查找或筛选内容的时使用的搜索域
Otherwise we will get every possible object
另外在当前项目中所有可能
in the project that can go in to this field.
被作为纹理的文件都显示在了这个资源选择器中
To associate a texture we simply
单击那个纹理的文件
click on the texture we want.
就可以将当前材料指定纹理
In this case fx_laser_orange.
这里是文件fx_laser_orange
If there is already an existing texture
如果想要将当前材料
associated with this field, and we want to remove it
已经选定的纹理去掉
we can select None.
我们只需要选择None
The other way is to simply drag and drop
另一种方式就是拖拽选取
a texture in to this field.
把纹理图片拖到点选选择的位置
Select Textures in the root of Assets
先在资源的根层级选择纹理
and drag fx_laser_orange on to our
把fx_laser_orange拖拽到
fx_bolt_orange material.
fx_bolt_orange材料上
and drop it in to the main texture field.
把它放到主纹理区域上
Both ways associate a texture to a material.
以上两种方法都可以将纹理与材料连接起来
If we look below the material in the Inspector
看一下Inspector视窗下方的的
we see a preview window where we can get
材料预览窗口
a sense of how this material will
我们可以大致了解到这个材质的
behave in our scene.
效果
Now to associate the material
现在要把材料连接到
with the VFX quad
VFX quad上去
we can simply drag the material on to the quad.
我们同样使用拖拽的方式把材料连接到quad上
Now if we look at the VFX game object
如果我们现在再看一眼VFX这个游戏对象
and inspect the mesh renderer
在网格渲染器这个组件中
we can see the fx_bolt_orange material
我们可以看到材料fx_bolt_orange
has been added to the top slot of the materials array.
在材料队列的顶部
Another way of associating the material
或者我们直接手动把需要连接的材料
with this game object is to populate
拖拽到当前游戏对象的
these slots in the materials array by hand.
材料队列的槽内
We can simply drag and drop a material
我们可以把材料拖拽到我们
in to the slots we need.
需要的槽孔内
If we swap to the game view however our
如果我们切回游戏视图
laser bolt looks like a dull streak
激光子弹看起来就像
in the middle of a big black square.
一个黑色方块中的一条平淡的条文
Not very flashy.
一点都不炫酷
What we need to do in this case is change
这里我们需要该一下
the shader we are using.
着色器
Just like when we created our background
就像我们当初改背景的那样
diffuse is not the best shader
默认的散射着色器对我们的武器来说
choice for our weapon.
并不是一个好的着色器
For our weapon we want the bright parts to
对于我们的武器来说,我们希望
add on top of the scene and the black parts
线的部分足够亮
to vanish.
黑的部分都消失掉
When looking at the VFX game object
让我们再看一眼VFX这个游戏对象
we can change the shader on the material.
我们把这个材料的着色器换一下
Choose Particles - Additive.
选Particles - Additive
With this shader black has a value
这个着色器里面黑色的值就是0
of 0 and will add nothing to the scene.
因此看起来黑色的部分就不见了
And white has a value of 255
白色的值是255
on all channels and will add
所有通道的值都是255
full white to the scene.
在场景内生成的是纯白色
All of the other colours will be added
所有的其他颜色是叠加在
on top of the existing background.
现有的背景颜色之上的
This will give us a strong, hot laser bolt.
这样我们就看到了一个闪亮炙热的镭射子弹了
We can also try mobile particles additive.
我们也可以试试mobile particles additive
For our game I don't see any noticeable issues
对于我们的游戏来说
with using the mobile shader.
使用手机着色器个并没有什么显著改变
It looks just fine when we look in the game view.
我们在游戏场景看的效果还可以
In many cases mobile shaders can be used
多数情况手机着色器
effectively in non-mobile games.
在非手机游戏中的效果也都不错
In general the mobile shaders will
整体上来说手机着色器
be more efficient with our game's resource budget,
在资源有限的情况下更有效一些
but in some cases may sacrifice either
但有些情况下手机着色器会牺牲掉质量
quality or control.
和不可控来保证效果
The main control that we will lose
当前游戏如果我们使用手机着色器
by using this mobile shader
我们将失去对
is the ability to change the tint colour,
tint colour这个选项的控制
which we don't need on our laser bolt.
这个选项对我们的镭射子弹来说没什么用
With our visual effects setup let's move
我们的视觉效果设定完了
on to setting up our logic.
让我们继续设定射击逻辑
If we look at our Bolt parent game object
察看一下子弹的父类
we can see that it has no components,
发现除了变形组建外
beyond the default transform component.
父类并没有什么组建
We will be moving these shots with physics
我们让这些射出的子弹按照物理法则运动
and, almost more importantly
更重要的是
we will be moving a collider in our game.
我们需要为这个子弹添加碰撞检测机
Both require the rigidbody component
以上两点都需要刚体组件
so let's click on Add Component.
因此我们点击Add Component
and select Physics - Rigidbody
选择Physics - Rigidbody
to add a rigidbody component to the Bolt game object.
为自弹游戏对象增加刚体组件
Deselect Use Gravity as we don't want our shots
把Use Gravity的钩选去掉
falling down off of the game plane.
我们并不想让我们的子弹从游戏平面掉下去
Next we need a collider to participate
然后我们需要一个碰撞检测机
in collisions.
来检测碰撞
Before we add one however we want
在添加新的碰撞检测机之前
to remove one.
我们先去除些没用的东西
Click on VFX to show our quad.
点击VFX看一下quad(四边形)
The stock quad is created with a
我们子弹的这个quad在创建的时候
mesh collider on it.
自带了一个网格碰撞检测机
We can disable the mesh renderer to see
我们先停用一下网格渲染
the green lines of this mesh collider.
这个绿色的线就是网格碰撞检测机
We don't need 2 colliders in this game
统一个游戏对象中不需要两个碰撞监测机
object family, but more importantly
更重要的是
we don't want a collider that sticks out
我们不需要一个范围如此大
so far to the sides
的碰撞检测机
beyond the image of our laser bolt.
它跟我们镭射子弹的图像外形差距太大了
This would mean what looks like a near miss
这意味着一个看起来并没有的碰撞
could cause a collision.
可能导致碰撞
One the mesh collider component
在网格碰撞检测机组件(英文字幕错了这里是On不是One)
use the context sensitive gear menu
点选右上角的小齿轮
and click on Remove Component.
点击Remove Component
This will remove the mesh collider component
这样网格碰撞检测机就被从
from the VFX game object.
VFX游戏对象中移除了
Now let's add the collider component
我们现在再给我们的游戏
we want for our game.
加一个我们需要的碰撞检测机
Click on the parent Bolt game object
点击子弹父类的游戏对象
and click on Add Component.
点击Add Component
Select Physics - Capsule Collider.
选择Physics - Capsule Collider
Now this looks like a sphere but it is
现在这个看起来是个球形
not, it is a capsule.
但它不是球形是胶囊形
A capsule is defined by 2 spheres
胶囊形是由2个球形或椭圆形和
or hemispheres, one at each end.
他们中间的空间定义的
and the space in between.
球形在胶囊的两端每端一个
We are looking at a capsule that is
我们需要的胶囊形状
as compact as possible, and there's no
是要足够的紧凑
space between the 2 end caps.
两端的球体半径要足够的小
So let's adjust the size of the capsule.
让我们改一下胶囊的尺寸
We can reduce the radius dramatically
我们可以把半径减小一些
as our bolt is long and thin.
因为我们的子弹是又细又长的
When we do we can see that the
我们发现
capsule is oriented differently from our bolt.
胶囊的方向与我们子弹的方向不一致
The default orientation, or direction of a capsule
胶囊默认的方向是沿着
is along the Y axis
Y轴的
to accommodate humanoid characters.
这是为了适应人形的角色
Let's change the direction to the Z axis.
我们把方向改成沿着Z轴
Now it's oriented with our Bolt VFX.
现在它的方向跟我们子弹VFX的方向是一致的了
Let's move in to a top-down position.
让我们再从上往下看看
This view will help us size the collider
这样我们可以从视觉上更好的
correctly to our visual effect.
调整我们碰撞检测机的大小
Let's pick a radius that best matches our image.
让我们选一个能恰好合适我们图像的半径
0.03 looks good.
0.03看起来挺合适
Now let's reduce the height to fit
现在我们在把长度减小一点
our image as well.
刚好符合图像的大小
0.5 looks good.
0.5不错
We don't need the outer glow to have any
我们不想让我们外围的光晕也有
physical effect in our game
这些物理效果
just the hot core of our laser bolt.
仅仅是最热的中心部分的镭射子弹就好了
Before we leave this collider component
在我们完成这个碰撞检测机之前
we need to set one other property.
我们需要设定一个别的属性
We need to select Is Trigger
我们需要钩选Is Trigger
to make this collider a trigger collider.
确保这个碰撞检测机是一个带触发器的碰撞检测机
For more information on triggers and colliders
更多关于触发器和碰撞检测机的信息请
please see the lesson linked below.
参考下方课程的连接
With the basic component setup
基本的组件已经设定好了
we now need to write our custom logic.
我们现在需要设定我们的个性化的逻辑代码
With the Bolt game object selected
我们选定子弹这个游戏对象
click on Add Component
点击Add Component
and choose New Script.
选择New Script
Name this script Mover.
把这个脚本命名为Mover
Confirm this choice to add it to Bolt.
确认后把这个脚本加到了Bolt中
Let's file Mover in to the Scripts folder
我们吧Mover移动到Scripts文件加
and open it for editing.
然后点击open打开编辑它
Again, let's remove the sample code.
我们还是要把自动添加好的代码删掉
So what do we need to write?
我们需要写什么呢?
That depends upon what we want our laser
这取决于我们想让我们的镭射子弹
bolt to do.
做什么
We want it to move automatically when
我们需要子弹在进入场景以后
it's added to the scene.
可以自动移动
We want the laser bolt to have it's own velocity,
镭射子弹要有自己的速度
which we can set through the rigidbody.
这个我们可以通过刚体组件来设定
So let's write void Start.
所以我们写下void Start
With Start the code we will write
使用Start的话我们的代码
will be executed on the very first frame
在对象实例化的时候就会
the object is instantiated.
开始执行了
Let's continue with rigidbody.velocity =
接下来我们写rigidbody.velocity =
Well what?
等于什么呢?
We want the laser bolt to travel along
我们想要镭射子弹
the Z axis towards the
沿着Z周运动
oncoming hazards the game will
来迎击小行星之类朝着玩家
throw at our player.
飞船飞过来的危险
The local Z axis of an object is
一个对象自身的Z轴也被
also known as it's transform forward.
称作它的transform forward(移动方向)
So let's finish with transform.forward.
所以我们在这写上代码transform.forward
We will want some control over how
我们需要控制
fast our laser bolt moves in our game
镭射子弹的速度
so let's add public float speed.
我们增加一个公共浮点形参数speed
and let's multiply transform.forward by speed.
我们将transform.forward与speed相乘
That's it. It's a very simple script.
完成了,这个脚本很简单
Save this script and return to Unity.
保存脚本回到Unity
We can see Bolt now has Speed as part of
我们可以看到Bolt对象的Mover组件
the Mover component we have just written
有了我们刚写的Speed属性
Our player is going to shoot many copies
我们的玩家将发射很多这种子弹的
or clones of this shot, so let's save this
副本或者克隆
game object as a prefab.
所以让我们把这个对象保存成预制件
The easiest way to do this is to drag
最简单的方法是把这个子弹
the Bolt game object from the Hierarchy view
从层级视图拖拽到
in to the Prefabs folder in Assets.
资源的Prefabs文件夹中
Click on Prefabs so we can see our Bolt prefab.
点击Prefabs文件夹我们可以看到子弹的预制件
Currently we have full access to the
目前我们对这个预制件有完全访问的权限
components on this prefab, but note that the
但是请注意一下,右侧的预览
preview window is open.
窗口是打开的
Even though we can scroll to see all of the
虽然我们仍然可以使用滚动条来看到
components on a game object.
对象的全部组件
If this preview window gets in the way
如果我们觉得这个预览窗口碍事
it can simply be dragged down and closed
我们可以把它拖到
against the bottom.
屏幕最底端就可以了
Let's set the speed value for our bolt.
我们现在为子弹设置一下速度
How fast was our ship travelling?
飞船的速度是多少来的?
10?
Our shots need to go faster than our ship
子弹肯定比飞船快
so let's try a speed value of 20.
所以我们先试试子弹速度为20
Lastly we only want an instance of
最后一点需要注意的是
the Bolt game object in our scene
只有飞船开火了以后
when our player fires it's weapon.
子弹才会产生
So let's delete our working instance
所以我们把我们正在研究的这个
of Bolt from the scene.
子弹从视图上删除
So save the scene.
保存一下视图
Turn off Maximise On Play
如果按钮Maximise On Play
if it's on and enter Play mode.
是打开的就把它关了,然后运行
To test the bolt, as we don't have any shooting code
我们没开火的代码,如何测试子弹
we can simply drag copies of the prefab
我们把子弹的预制件拖拽到
in to the hierarchy window
正在运行的游戏的
while the game is running.
层级视图的视窗上就行了
And they work as we expected.
子弹运行的跟我们计划的一样
Of they go towards the top of the screen.
它们飞向了屏幕的顶端
These are our shots with their VFX
这就是我们使用了VFX和我们设定的逻辑
and their logic.
的子弹
In the next assignment we will write the code
在下一章节我们将编写
for our player to fire these in the game.
游戏中飞船发射子弹的代码